<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://resources.qdexapps.com/schema/v1/QDocument.xsd" name="myDocument" id="G088BC709_A1D9_4F11_8B7D_5AAE4FB785BB">

  <!-- Meta Data -->
  <metadata>
    <title>NUM-5.2-Rates of Change</title>
    <creator>Sidique</creator>
    <coverImage src="resources/cover.png" />
    <abstract>This document is for testing purposes only. The material that is presented here should be treated as an example only.</abstract>
  </metadata>

  <include src="resources/curriculumStyles.xml" />
  <include src="resources/Utilities.xml" />
  <include src="resources/plotTools.xml" />

  <!--                                      Header & Footer START                                         -->
  <header style="backgroundColor">
    <stack style="center" orientation="horizontal">
      <p style="whiteColor">Amanda Koon</p>
      <p style="whiteColor rightText">NUMERACY</p>
    </stack>
  </header>
  <footer style="backgroundColor">
    <stack orientation="horizontal">
      <image style="tiny" src="resources/logo1.png" inspect="false" />
      <p style="fontColor">
        <style>
          <numbering suffix="true" counter="pages" />
          <textAlignment>center</textAlignment>
          <marginTop>30</marginTop>
          <foreground color="255 255 255" />
        </style>
      </p>
      <image style="tiny" src="resources/logo2.png" inspect="false" />
    </stack>
  </footer>

  <!-- Section 1 -->
  <section name="section1" style="pageLayout">
    <title style="chapterTitle">5.2 Rates of Change</title>
    <image src="resources/riserun.png" />
    <stack style="contentBG">
      <p>Rates of change describes the change of a value over a certain amount of time. You may have heard of some Rates of Change already such as speed (disatnce over time) or even
      wage (dollars over time). Rates of Change is an important concepts in math that helps us look at the bigger picture. In this module we will take a look at the precise definition of Rates of Change,
      defining average rates of change, instantaneous rate of change and go through simulations and examples to help understand the concept.</p>
    </stack>
  </section>

  <sectionNoTitle style="pageLayout" name="section2">
    <p style="sectionHeading">Definition of a Rate of Change</p>
    <stack style="contentBG">
      <p>A Rate of Change can be defined as the change of a dependant variable over time. The formula we use to calculate rate of change is known
      as the rise over run formula: $ \frac{ \triangle y}{ \triangle x} = \frac{y_{2} - y_{1}}{x_{2} - x_{1}}$</p>
      <p>Rates of change have units in the form $ \frac{Dependant \; Variable}{Time} $</p>
      <p style="subSectionHeading">
        Average Rate of Change
      </p>
      <p>The average rate of change is the rate of change over a period of time.</p>
      <p style="subSectionHeading">
        Instantaneous Rate of Change
      </p>
      <p>The instantaneous rate of change is the rate of change at a particular time.</p>
      <p>For an example, a driver on the highway looks at their speed and it reads $ 100 \frac{km}{h} $. This is their instantaneous rate of change.
      When the driver finally reaches his destination, they take note that it took 1 hour to travel 50 kilometres.</p>
      <p>In this example, when the driver noted their speed, it was the instantaenous rate of change they saw.</p>
      <p>The average rate of change is $ 50 \frac{km}{hour} $ since it took the driver 1 hour to drive 50km. The average rate of change gives information about
      the whole trip compared to just a single moment in time. But note that the average rate of change does not state the driver was travelling at $ 120 \frac{km}{hour} $</p>
    </stack>
    
  </sectionNoTitle>
  
  <sectionNoTitle style="pageLayout" name="section3">
    <p style="sectionHeading">Rate of Change Simulation</p>
    <stack style="contentBG">
      <p>Use the simulation below to visualize what the slope of a function looks like. Pan your finger around the plot to see the rise over run of the slope.</p>
      
    </stack>
  </sectionNoTitle>

</document>